So, what is SEO in 2026? Well, it's
getting very confusing because you have
all kind of definitions floating around.
We have SEO, we have AI SEO, we have
search engine optimization versus search
everywhere optimization. Then you throw
in the new acronyms. You've got answer
engine optimization, AEO. You've got
generative engine optimization, GEO.
Okay? And so, it's just getting
absolutely crazy at this point. So, in
this video, I'm going to bring this all
together and show you what SEO actually
is in 2026, all the different
components, so you can truly understand
how to get results, not just in
traditional search, but also on these AI
platforms. And so, my name is Nathan
Gotch. I've been doing SEO for over a
decade, and I've led hundreds of
successful SEO campaigns in legal,
health, B2B SaaS, you name it. I've seen
pretty much every scenario that you can
think of. And I also run two SEO
companies and that are heavily driven by
AI. So, I have Rankability, and I also
have Search OS. And just if you need to
see other proof that I'm not just some
random guy talking on YouTube, you can
go to Amazon, you can see I'm the author
of one of the best-selling books on how
to start an SEO business, and I'm also
the upcoming author of AI SEO for
Dummies, okay? So, I eat, breathe, and
sleep SEO and AI search and AI in
general, using AI in every single thing
that I do, okay? So, let's talk about
it. So, SEO in 2026.
Let's begin with the simple part here is
uh the opportunities, okay? Let's just
start with the opportunities. So,
when it comes to SEO, my true definition
of SEO is search everywhere
optimization, okay? Because it is truly
the broadest umbrella that properly
defines what we're doing. So, I'm going
to give you a couple examples So, let's
begin with the most obvious part of SEO,
which is we're going to go ahead and I'm
just going to fill this out as we go.
So, traditional search, okay? So, what
is traditional search? Well,
it is Google,
Bing,
DuckDuckGo,
Yahoo,
and Brave, okay? And there's some others
we could throw in there, too. But,
essentially, a traditional search
engine, what everyone knows. You got the
10 blue links. It's just an index of web
pages, okay? This still matters, but not
the way that you might think, okay? So,
number one is
yes, you can still get traffic, okay?
You can still get traffic through this.
It's just decreasing every single day
because of organic CTRs getting more
challenging to come by, okay? Because
there's so many other things that are
going on now in in the SERPs. So, but
traditionally, you would rank for, you
know, rank your web page or your
website, and you would drive clicks uh
through this traditional index. Now,
what I'm going to show you here in a
second is this still matters, but the
reason why it matters is because it
actually is the fuel for the AI
platforms, okay? So, let's talk about
that. So, we've got our opportunities,
we've got our traditional search. Next,
we're going to talk about AI, okay? So,
what is AI? And specifically, let's get
I mean, more specifically here, AI
search, okay? So, there's two components
of AI search. Number one is the static
corpus, okay?
And what this means is that when a when
you go into Chat GPT and you search
something like, "What is the moon?" and
Chat GPT just responds to you without
going and doing any research on the
internet, it's pulling from its static
corpus. In other words, it's pulling
from its existing knowledge, right? It's
existing knowledge, it's existing
training data, and it's giving you an
answer, okay?
As an AI SEO expert, you need to know
that you want to influence the static
corpus, which is that
initial training data, and you also want
to influence, which I'll show you here
in a second, is any answers that are
derived from web search, okay? Now, on
this front here, this is what's
interesting about static corpus,
is there's a training
cut-off date, okay?
So, GPT-5.4 just came out, and it is
there's a training date. So, as soon as
that date hits, when it ingests all of
this information, you can't influence
this anymore. So, if the training date
was 6 months ago, whatever you got in
prior to that point is going to be baked
into the static corpus. Anything after
that, it's invisible. It's invisible to
the AI models. So, I don't know if this
is always going to be the case, but for
now, this is the case. This is how it
works. So, they go through these big
training cycles, they train the model,
they they cut off the model from any new
training data, and then they release
that model, right? And so, it's kind of
your whenever you're working with any
model, you're technically looking maybe
three, potentially even 6 months in the
past, okay?
Now, how have AI platforms overcome
this? Well, you know, if you if you need
up-to-date information about anything,
you need to ultimately go to the
internet, right? Because search engines
are the most up-to-date source for
information. So, these AI platforms,
they realized that the best way to stay
up-to-date and not just be feeding
outdated information to users, they've
added the web search component, okay?
Now, web search, this is also known as
rag, which is retrieval augmented
generation, super geeky term, but in
essence, what's going on here is when
you when you search something like, you
know,
"What are the best baseball cleats right
now in 2026,
Chat GPT is not just going to give you
that answer, right? It's going to go to
the web, it's going to look for
opportunities to enhance that answer,
get more accuracy, and deliver an
accurate, up-to-date response to the
user, okay? Now, here's where SEO comes
in.
Come to find out, one of the top sources
of retrieval, where they go and get
information, happens to be search. So,
watch this. This is the crazy part. Go
like this. This is going to get really
messy super fast, but I just want to
show you for demonstration, okay?
This is actually all interconnected,
okay? You can see that web search is
actually traditional search. And that's
why I'm telling you that traditional
search is still critical. If you want to
be able to influence the output from
these AI search platforms, if you want
to be able to bake in your brand into
those answers,
you got to do well on traditional
search. This has not gone anywhere. You
still have to do this, okay? So, those
are the kind of like key components you
need to be thinking about. Now, when it
comes to AI search, what what is it What
are the platforms that actually matter,
okay?
So, first we can talk about Google,
because Google is the, you know, the
most popular traditional search engine,
but it also has multiple AI products
that you need to be paying attention to.
And no, they are not the same. Every
single AI product that Google has
doesn't exactly produce the same
outcome. And that's because AI in
general, when it gives you an answer,
it's it's a non-deterministic answer.
It's very difficult to get AI to give
you the same exact answer across
multiple platforms. It just really does
not happen. It's basically impossible.
So, for Google, it's got multiple AI
products you need to be thinking about.
So, we have AI overviews, and these are
what you see when you're in traditional
Google search, right? So, if we We just
run a real quick one, you know, what are
the best
baseball cleats or best Yeah, that's a
good one. Let's that. Auto suggests. So,
you can see here AI overview. This is
This is what pops up directly in the
SERPs, okay? And you can see it's very
disruptive to the traditional SERPs,
right? We see it. It completely
dominates. It It like just pushes
everything below the fold, okay? So,
this is a critical AI product that we
need to be paying attention to. Now,
Google's Google is is
uh
technology is being used in the
underlying layer across all their AI
products. It's still Gemini, but it's
just the way that these are structured,
the uh citations that they use is never
exactly the same. And I'll show you how
to you know, how to track this, but this
is critical. So, AI product number one,
if you're selling baseball cards, you
need to be here, okay? You want to be in
the AI answer, but you also want to be
one of the citations. And in addition to
being one of the citations, you also
want your brand to be cited on the other
citations as much as possible, okay?
So, going back to this,
so we have AI overviews, all right? Next
one is Google AI
mode, okay? I don't need to put Google
twice because we know we're talking
about here. All right. So, we'll go to
AI mode. Once again, you're in here.
You're on Google. You click on AI mode.
Boom. You're going to get a slightly
different answer than what you just got
in AI overviews, okay? And we can even
see,
just based on my memory here, uh the
citation sources are even different in
this initial run here, okay? So, we're
seeing that we've got a different set of
citations, different set of retrieval
sources, and even the answer itself is
slightly different, okay? So, these are
not the same, and we know this because
in Rankability, we track this. We track
uh performance in AI mode, and we track
performance in AI overviews, and you
don't always see the same stuff. And
then the third Google AI product that
you need to know about is Google Gemini.
So, there are searches being conducted
here all the time. They're just probably
a little bit different. They're probably
a little more context. They're not, you
know, kind of these short queries.
They're probably much longer queries in
here. But still, there is still search
demand occurring on Gemini. So, we're
going to go back over here. And so, we
have just in Google alone, we have AI
overviews, we have AI mode, and we have
Gemini. Okay? Now, aside from that, the
the next biggest AI platform you need to
pay attention to goes without saying,
which is ChatGPT. Okay? We know that
ChatGPT has This is over, you know, last
time they reported this, I think it's
700 million weekly active users. So,
it's probably much more than that now.
And it continues to grow. So, of the AI
platform specifically, if you exclude
traditional search, ChatGPT has I I
think the last report was that they have
over 50% of the market. Okay? So, it's a
lot, right? They're huge. So, we have to
be paying attention. We have to be
tracking our performance on these
critical platforms. Now, let's talk
about some of the other platforms that
are also important, just not as
important as these two bigger monsters
here. So, we'll go and talk about We
have aside from that, we have Claude,
which is growing very fast, which is
through Anthropic, the company.
A lot of people are using Claude for,
you know, co-work and
all of the different functions that
Claude has. So, you need to pay
attention to it. Okay? We also have
Perplexity. Also very popular search
engine, AI search engine, but just not
as big as these other ones. Okay? We
also have Grok. Lots of people use Grok.
And Grok is unique because it is heavily
fueled by X. So, a lot of the retrieval
sources are actually X. So, it makes it
unique in that way. Okay? And then we
have, you know, Microsoft Copilot, which
is also a big one if you're a big
Microsoft user.
And And
that's Those are like probably the core
ones I'd be paying attention to. Of
course, you can throw in like Deep Seek
and so on and so forth, okay? So,
there's a significant amount of
platforms that we need to be thinking
about. And these are all the AI-driven
platforms that we need to be paying
attention to, okay? So, as you can tell,
SEO is uh much more than just this. It
used to be just this, but now when you
add in all these other opportunities,
you start to see that this is much more
than just uh traditional SEO, okay? Now,
there's more though. We're just getting
started. That's Those are just those
opportunities. No worry.
This is not as complicated as it might
seem right now, okay? Because a lot of
these platforms here, they're they
basically function the same way, okay?
You're not They're not like, you know,
each one is different. They all just
copy each other. So, that's the good
news. They just copy each other. So, the
the optimization process is quite
similar across most of the platforms.
You're not going to You're going to see
it it produces different outcomes,
different answers, different citations.
Yes, it's all different cuz just the way
that it's composed in these AI answers,
but you'll see it's not that wildly
different, okay?
All right. So, the next one here we want
definitely be focused on is local, okay?
And when it comes to local, it's pretty
much Google all day, okay? Google
dominates local queries. It's not even
close. Uh it is definitely the number
one platform for local queries. And when
it comes to local queries, it's quite
simple. It's the Google Business
Profile, okay? The Google Business
Profile is the center of local
performance on Google. And it's not just
that uh for traditional, you know, the
local pack, which we know you need a
Google Business Profile to show up
there. We've got the local pack, which
is critical. But, how you perform in the
local pack also dictates how you perform
in uh Google's AI mode. So, it's very,
very important when people are
conducting uh
uh local queries
with commercial intent, okay? So, that
would be something like, you know, we'll
do an example. Might be like, you know,
who's the best plumber
near me, okay? And AI mode is very good
at knowing your location, so you
wouldn't even need to add that localized
you wouldn't need add that modifier in
there. It would probably still give you
a pretty good answer. But, if you wanted
a better answer, you'd say, you know,
who's the best plumber in, you know,
Chesterfield, right? That would
obviously produce a better result, a
more relevant result, because AI mode is
not going to be 100% accurate. Now, what
it does though, is when it conducts when
it goes through this process, um, I'm
getting a little OCD here, so I need to
make the padding more.
Um, so, when it goes through this
process, runs this query, and it gives
an answer, okay? What it actually is
going to do is it's going to go actually
and look in local search, and it's look
specifically at what businesses are
showing up in the local pack, okay? And
so, when it produces that answer,
it's going to show it's going to show
businesses, right? You're going to see
businesses popping up in that answer.
But, they're derived directly from the
local pack, okay? So, you can see how
this all kind of works together, right?
And so, we can even just I'll just run a
real quick test so you can see this. So,
we'll look at, uh, who's the best
plumber in Chesterfield, Missouri, okay?
And of course, Google can't give you
that exact answer, cuz it can't just
choose one, but you can see here in AI
overviews, you'll see that the the
answers that are derived here are
different than the answers that will be
derived in AI mode. So, in AI in AI
overviews, you'll see that it's actually
pulling from a lot of, uh, websites,
okay? So, Angie's Angie's List, Yelp,
even a actual business in that location,
okay? so this shows that traditional
search is critical and also being on
these other third-party platforms is
critical if you want to influence the AI
overview, okay? But then we go over to
AI mode and this is where things will
get a lot different because more than
likely what we'll see here is it's going
to pull it will pull from those sources
again, but then you'll see it actually
is going to show Google Business
Profiles in here, okay? And these are
based on our data we've seen that these
are usually just the businesses that
perform well in local pack. It's It's
literally that simple. Like the business
that perform well in the local pack here
uh or it perform in the local pack
perform well in Google AI mode, okay?
So, if you want better performance in
Google AI mode, you need to do well in
the local pack. That is the leading
uh opportunity there, okay? And in
addition to the traditional search as
well, okay?
All right. And then when it comes to the
other AI platforms, this is where things
get a little interesting is we'll say
non-Google.
So, non-Google platforms,
they are much more heavily driven by the
third-party platforms. So, when you go
into ChatGPT and we do the same exact
we'll run this same exact query
in ChatGPT
and we'll use 5.4. So, uh
who's the best plumber in Chesterfield,
Missouri right now?
All right, so we're going to run this
and you'll it will more than likely is
going to go and trigger a web search or
do retrieval. So, you'll see when it
does this thinking here, this means it's
going and doing research, okay? So,
you'll see here it's actually going to
kind of uh dictate what it's doing, but
it's going to go and do the do the
research and what you're going to find
here is it's not just going to be
searching it's not going to search
Google, right? It's going to search
Angie, it's going to search Yelp. Uh
it's going to go to it's going to go to
search engines more than likely being,
um but you'll see a lot of this stuff is
going to be very similar to what you'll
see in the traditional search results.
So, but you see it went directly to
Angie. So, that was probably a direct
retrieval. This was not it going to
search. So, this is important to
understand that it's not always going to
search engines, right? Sometimes it is
going direct uh direct retrieval, right?
So, we can see now the retrieval sources
here. This is where the magic happens
because if you want to be a brand that
pops up in this AI answer, you need to
be in these retrieval sources. So, the
good news is you just you just look at
all these retrieval sources and see is
our brand actually here? Like, are we
listed on these retrieval sources? Yes
or no? It's simple as that. And if your
answer is no, that's the work that you
have to do. You go in here, you start
you build a profile there, you optimize
your profile, you start driving reviews
on Angie, Better Business Bureau,
whatever's showing up in these
citations, this is the work, right? This
is where you need to go and and take
action there to to influence this
answer. Remember, this answer is not a
magical thing that occurs. It's just
It's doing research
and then it's presenting an answer that
it's attempting to be objective based on
the research that it did. The AI does
not know who's the best plumber. All
it's doing is getting that raw material
and then it's able to produce
at least it's attempting to produce
something that's objective, right?
That's what it's trying to do, okay? So,
for us, our goal to influence this is we
have to be here, okay? Simple as that.
Okay, so we're good. We've got local and
you're probably think, all right, yeah,
I guess we're good to go. That's SEO. Uh
well, no.
There's actually more. So, let's
continue down this way. So, we'll move
this over here. This is getting out of
control. All right, I'll put it like
this. All right, so the next one here
um oh, let's see.
All right.
Okay. So, the next one is actually
e-commerce. So, obviously, these are not
all going to be applicable to every
industry, but we do have e-commerce
search, okay? And it within this bucket,
you have Amazon, Walmart,
Etsy,
uh and even eBay. eBay's had quite the
resurgence recently. So, you know, those
are all platforms where you can you can
actually do SEO on these platforms,
right? You could do Amazon SEO. You can
do Walmart SEO. This is why
understanding SEO in general is so
incredibly powerful because you can
apply the same principles of relevance
across any platform, right? Relevance is
key, okay? So, and even like, you know,
I'll kind of give you a meta example
here, but like right now this video that
I'm doing is going to be for the next
opportunity, which we'll go ahead and
click. Let's go this way.
This is getting wild. One second here.
Okay, we'll bring this over here.
And we'll bring this one over here.
Okay. So, the next one here is actually
going to be social. I I don't really
like putting YouTube into social, but
for the sake of this video, we'll just
say that, okay? So, we have social
search, right? The number one social
search, if you want to call it, is
YouTube, okay? It's not even close.
YouTube is the second most popular
website on the internet besides
google.com. So,
it is a place that you need to be,
and you need to understand SEO for
YouTube specifically. And here's the
good news about doing SEO across any
platform. If you just understand that
you need to create relevant content to
your subject matter expertise, and you
need to consistently do that all the
time to retain the topical relevance of
your channel, of your Instagram profile,
of whatever it is, that's the number one
thing that's going to help you, okay?
So, on YouTube, you want to pick a
particular niche that you want to focus
in on. Unless you're some sort of
lifestyle blogger, and you're trying to
do that, okay, cool, but I'm talking
specifically about B2B. If you're in
B2B, you need to pick a niche. You need
to specialize in that niche and all of
your content needs to focus on that for
an extended amount of time. If you're
going to be
you know, you're a SEO agency for
chiropractors,
all of your content should be about SEO
for chiropractors. Like and you
shouldn't produce anything else until it
is abundantly clear to the algorithms
that that's what you do, okay? And then
there's this compound effect. The more
that you focus in on that, the better it
will do. And I'll give you a small
example. Like on my channel,
I've been talking about SEO on my
channel since 2017, okay? So I have a
lot of
raw material to work with, but as soon
as I talk about a topic that's aside
from SEO. Like let's say I go totally
off the rails. I'm like, I'm going to do
Facebook ads, you know, today. Um it
will probably do very poorly, okay?
Very, very poorly because the algorithms
will be very confused why all of a
sudden now I'm talking about Facebook
ads.
Right? And it's not going to probably
put that in the in front of the right
audience because I've established that
my focus on my channel is SEO AI search
and so on and so forth, okay? So
anything directly to related to SEO. So
that's a
it's an advantage for performance. It's
a disadvantage if you want to expand
outside of that niche, okay? So but it's
not impossible either by the way. If you
want to expand into a
adjacent vertical or adjacent niche, um
you would just need to produce a similar
volume of content around that one topic
to retrain the algorithms, right? So but
you can't just do kind of one-off stuff.
It's not really going to do anything,
all right? So YouTube is absolutely
huge. And in addition to YouTube, you
should be thinking about search across
all of these other platforms. So you
know, LinkedIn obviously being optimized
there. You got X. You've got Pinterest.
You've got obviously TikTok. You've got
Instagram. You've got Facebook and so on
and and forth, okay? This is all the
social search. So, and there's this is
like this is probably 95% of search,
like all the stuff I just mentioned, but
you also have like, you know, app store
optimization and other stuff like that.
But, those are all going to be
case-by-case basis. For most businesses,
you're going to be, you know, the the
core ones that really matter for every
business, not just, you know, not just
specific use cases. Obviously,
traditional search cuz we know this
fuels. This is the fuel. Um let's see if
I can turn this to a different color.
This is the fuel for AI platforms. So,
doing well here is critical.
AI search, goes without saying. Every
business needs to be thinking about AI
search. Every single business. It does
not matter what you do. It matters for
every business. So, these two are
universal for every business.
Traditional search and AI search, goes
without saying, okay? Then you just pop
in, you know, your specific vertical use
case, okay? So, those are the
opportunities. And as you can tell, SEO
is much more than just ranking in blue
links, okay? And I think that's what's
really important here is like if you're
going to do well at SEO, if you're going
to sell SEO to businesses, you're going
to help businesses with SEO, uh you're
going to try to do SEO yourself, this is
the mindset you have to have. You're not
just thinking, "Oh, I'm just going to
rank in traditional search and
everything's going to go well."
Not necessarily, okay? Not necessarily.
And I'll show you a quick example of
this inside of Rankability.
You'll see um this is a best SEO content
optimization tool. So, very competitive
keyword, okay? You can see Rankability
absolutely crushes it in traditional
search, okay? I mean, we're we could do
better. Yes, there's always more room
for improvement, but like it's doing
really, really well, okay? But, then you
go to the AI answers and we're not
number one.
Right? So, and then we've seen this
repeated over and over and over. Just
because you're doing well in traditional
search for your one URL, that's not
enough to influence every AI platform,
right? Because that's just one citation
source, right? You're just one citation
source among many. And as I just showed
you in this example, there's many
citation sources that happen. So you
need to be visible across all those
citation sources. So we see gaps here,
and these gaps
are are opportunities, okay? I see like,
okay, we're not doing well in ChatGPT.
All right, so we click on ChatGPT and
see, okay, well, why is that? Well,
number one, we're you're we're
definitely not mentioned here. So we got
to go figure out what citations is
ChatGPT using? What retrieval sources is
ChatGPT using? Then I'm going to go and
make sure that our brand is present on
those platforms, right? And so you can
go into the AI citations like this, and
you can see, you know, once again,
Rankability has a lot of citation
coverage, right? Across five different
AI platforms, we're being cited, okay?
But once again, that's just one. That's
just one one. So we can see mentions.
You can even see where you're mentioned
in here, which is also helpful, right?
We want to see, what are the platforms
where we actually are mentioned? But
what are the ones where we're completely
invisible, right? And so we see here, we
got Zapier, Marketer Milk, like all
these different platforms where we
absolutely would want to be a citation
source. And if you filter through this,
this is where it gets interesting.
So we'll go to all, and then we'll
filter out. We know like we know that
ChatGPT we're not doing well on. So we
just click on ChatGPT, and we can see
the core citation sources of ChatGPT.
So, okay, cool, TechRadar. I guess I
need to be present there because they
have three they're used three times as a
citation source, right? So I should be
trying to figure out ways to get brand
coverage on TechRadar, okay? This is all
you have to do. You just find those
gaps,
and then you go and try to figure out a
strategy to get coverage on those those
websites, okay? This is why, you know,
thinking about traditional link building
is not really the way you should be
thinking anymore. You should be thinking
about, okay, no, my prospects are the
prospects that are being used as a
common source of retrieval. And then you
go and get your brand mentioned there.
It doesn't matter whether it's a link or
just a brand mention. You could
literally have an unlinked brand mention
on this particular website, and that
still would influence AI platforms,
okay? The game has changed in that way,
okay?
All right, so going back to this. So we
know the opportunities, we know what we
need to do. Now,
what are a couple things as far as
goals? So pull this over here.
And so there's kind of
a couple goals that we need to be
thinking about. Number one is we need to
rank in traditional search
with our own website.
Goes without saying, okay? That has not
changed. We should still be trying to do
that. That's still very important
because this is something we can
control. We can actually produce
content. We can try to attack many
different queries, many different
angles. Um we we can just, you know, use
our own website. Now, for our own
website to rank well in traditional
search, it's pretty simple. You know,
really uh efficient technical SEO, good
loading speed, mobile experience,
security, all this stuff that's real
basic stuff, okay? But then, aside from
that, creating pages around our core
subject matter expertise, right? So just
building as many pages of those as we
can around our core expertise, uh and
filling in every gap that we can find.
And then backlinks, okay? Getting links
from relevant, high-quality websites to
your website is the most important
ranking variable for traditional search,
okay? So we still want to rank our own
website. But we also want to rank
other properties outside of
outside of our website. So I'll just say
outside of website.
Now I'll show you an example of this.
We'll look up uh let's see. We'll go
into here.
And we'll search something like
um we'll just do a quick analysis. We'll
do like best SEO tools. Okay, so we'll
run this.
And what we're going to see here is, you
know, you Yes, if you can get your one
URL to rank, that's great. Okay, that's
super good. But you'd also like to have
rankings across other platforms. So in
particular, when it comes to Google,
YouTube is incredibly powerful, right?
YouTube is one of the best sources to uh
to ultimately influence the AI
platforms. YouTube is used quite a bit
as a retrieval source. So we we want to
have a presence on YouTube, okay? And so
like this video here that I'm currently
doing, main keyword of this video is
what is SEO. So I'm saying this very
clearly in my script. The purpose of
this video is to teach people what is
SEO in 2026, okay? So when you say that
in your video, it's actually the AI
platforms use the transcription. So
that's why you want to be really clear
about your videos, what you're actually
what it's all about. If it's just kind
of like meandering topics, you don't
really know what it's about, it's going
to be harder for that video to be placed
not just on YouTube, but also in
traditional Google search, and also um
the AI platforms will struggle, right?
So you don't want to have that. Now,
when we look at this, a couple things I
want to show you here. So number one is
like yes, you can rank in traditional
search, but you can see there's a lot of
other things you want to be thinking
about as you want to also rank on
YouTube, okay? Cuz this gives us an
opportunity to actually show up in
traditional search if it's a wildly
competitive keyword, right? If it's a
wildly competitive keyword, you might
have a better chance of ranking on
YouTube than you do in traditional,
okay? Cuz you can see like you look at
the strength of some of these websites,
it's a lot, right? Like each of these
websites, the domain score is very, very
high. So, you'd have to be you'd have to
really do something spectacular and and
invest a significant amount of money
into links just to show up, you know, in
the top three. And even if you show up
in the top three, you're competing with
so many other search features. Okay? So,
you want to be thinking about that. Um
but then we go into YouTube, you know,
typically you might have a better chance
of performing here, right? So, you can
see like ranking number one in YouTube
with the video that's over a year old,
okay? Now, in traditional search, you're
probably not going to get away with
having stuff that's a year old, right?
It's probably not going to work as well.
So, once again, what you want to be
thinking about is how do we rank
on platforms that are known to do very
well in traditional search, okay? So,
that's the key. You don't just want to
Oh, I'm just going to start creating
content everywhere. You actually that's
not what you want to You want to create
really targeted content um on platforms
that already have good SEO performance
because we know that, as I mentioned
before, traditional search is used quite
a bit in retrieval. So, some that I like
to do uh will be YouTube is we know is
very good for Google. Um we also have
LinkedIn articles specifically.
These rank really well. Um and if we
look up like even uh let's see like open
claw Let's see, I don't even know what
this is ranking. Open claw SEO, okay?
And we'll see if there's any LinkedIn
post popping up here. Okay, so you can
see here, right away, there's a LinkedIn
post popping up here. This is what I'm
talking about, right? And like once
again, another LinkedIn post. Actually,
Instagram is actually popping up here,
which is interesting.
Um go over here. Here's another one here
uh from me. Another one actually from
here from me from X. So, we see X is
starting to get better indexation as
well and even Facebook, okay? So, you
can see you can use these other
platforms to your advantage, right? So,
we've got, you know, LinkedIn articles,
we've got X now. I didn't actually think
X would get indexed that well, but there
it is. We got IG, so all these platforms
that can that can help us because of
their super powerful authority can help
us drive a lot of visibility, you know,
for our business ultimately in search.
And then of course I forgot the most
obvious ones, which is Reddit
and Quora, okay? These are critical as
well. So, this is what you want to be
thinking about is like, I'm not just
ranking our one URL. I rank our one URL,
then what I do is I immediately start
going attacking these topics
across these other platforms, okay? To
try to
drive as much
visibility in traditional search and and
capture as much real estate as possible
around the topics that really matter for
us, okay? So, those are the two kind of
critical pieces for, you know, the
standard goals, but then in addition to
that, the kind of lagging goal we're
going for is to get
our brand mentioned
in AI answers, okay? So, specifically
for
queries
with commercial intent, okay? So, an
example would be like, you know, what
are the best
AI SEO tools for agencies right now,
right? And so, if someone searches that,
we would want Rankability to be in that
answer, right? And if we're not,
we've got work to do, okay? So, that's a
big one here. And then in addition to
that goal, we also want to become a top
source of
of retrieval.
That's very important. So, like our
website becomes one of the top sources
of retrieval, that's a big one. And then
the last one here is
we want to be present
on the top sources
of retrieval, okay?
>> [snorts]
>> And I can't spell. So, let's try that
again. All right, there we go. All
right, so these are kind of the core
goals you need to be thinking about.
Okay, this is very important.
As you can tell, our goals are not just
about, "Hey, let's rank our one webpage
anymore." There's multiple goals you
need to be thinking about, and this is
why SEO is much more than what it's ever
been before, but that makes it exciting.
There's a lot of new opportunities that
are going on, and if you understand all
of this, you're going to be incredibly
valuable to the marketplace. Okay, so
now moving on to a couple other things
I'm going to be thinking about here is
well, we'll quickly talk about threats.
The threats are not as severe as people
think they are. You'll probably see
people saying all the time that SEO is
dead and all this stuff, but the reality
is, yes, the old school SEO is not a
good idea if that's all you're going to
do. If you're just going to be thinking
about traditional search and ranking
your
one URL for one keyword, yes, you are
definitely going to be in trouble. But,
if you're thinking about SEO as the way
I'm describing it here, you're going to
be fine if you understand how to do
this, okay? Because it's not easy to
actually execute this work, okay?
Everything I'm describing to you, this
is this is not a simple process to
execute, and no, you can't just open up
ChatGPT and figure this all out for you.
There is still skill involved. There
still is execution capabilities
involved, okay? So, we'll go down here
and execution's the next big one, okay?
So, how do you actually get results?
Let's talk about that. How do you
actually get results in traditional
search? Well, you have to understand the
strategy, obviously, and I've talked
I've touched on a lot of different
points here.
Um but, there is actually like
we're in a very unique time right now,
because number one, you can use AI in
general, right, to help you with
execution. So, of course, the you know,
the the most basic form is using ChatGPT
and Gemini and Claude to help you out
with some stuff. Have it ask questions,
have it develop some basic code stuff,
um do some uh deep research and data
analysis.
Um it can actually kind of help you
formulate strategy a little bit. It's
okay at that. Um this is like we'll call
this like
beginner level AI execution for SEO,
okay?
But then you can go to the next level,
which brings in agents, okay? And agents
are the next level of this where you can
actually instead of just talking and
chatting with the AI and copying and
pasting stuff, you actually have the
agent go out and do work for you. So,
I'll give you a small example of this.
All right, so we'll go into
um
we'll go into Search OS and I'll copy a
prompt so you can see what this looks
like using Claude Co-Work, okay? So,
we'll go um let's actually go into here.
Go to library. So, in the agent skills,
this is one thing you want to first like
for any agents that you're going to be
working with, whether it's Open Claw or
uh Claude Co-Work, um you want to start
to be thinking about these skills. Now,
skills are not SOPs. Skills are specific
um the it's like a skill that you a
human would have, right? You give a
skill to the agent and it executes that
skill and based on the output that it
produces from the skill that you had
given it, you then correct course,
right? So, if it does a good job, you
continue on. If it does a poor job, you
iterate and you improve and you keep
expanding that skill further and
further. So, treat your agents like an
entry-level employee where you got to
continually compound the um the skill
over time, right? So, you may think
you've got a good kind of idea of like,
"Okay, here's the skill, go and
execute." But the the reality is in in
the in practicality when you actually
get that output, very rarely is it going
to be be exactly what you want out of
the gate. So, you have to continually
work with it over and over and over
until eventually it's doing what it
needs to do. So, you can see here like I
have the lead PM agent
project management. This is one thing
I've basically been able to systematize
almost fully using my agent specifically
in Open Claw. So, Open Claw manages all
of our projects inside of Search OS and
I do it through the Search OS API. So,
I've given Open Claw the API and so when
I say, "Hey, I need you to go and um
assign this work or I need you to go and
organize this uh
organize our board, organize our
projects." It can do that. It can also
assign work to people. It can manage the
workload. It can do all that, okay? But
only because I've been training it over
and over and over and over to the point
where it can actually do that, okay?
Now, if you don't want to use something
crazy like Open Claw, which is much more
intense and pretty intimidating,
Claw is probably easier, okay? So, you
can go over to like you can use AI
prompts. I've got a bunch of AI prompts
in here. So, we'll do a small one like
um Chamber of Commerce finder, okay? So,
let's copy this over.
So, then you would just go into
Google
and what I do is I open up the Open Claw
uh a chat window here, okay? And so, for
me, I'm pretty aggressive with this. I
basically let it just
run. I let it just do its stuff. Um but
basically you drop this in here and you
want to have you obviously want to have
a good prompt, okay? Like that is the
key to this being successful. So, in
this case,
uh I'd be doing some sort of link
prospecting for a local business, okay?
So, you put in the prompt, you fill in
all your stuff, and then you submit that
prompt, and then Claude on this one tab
will go and conduct this research for
you, okay?
Incredibly powerful, right? Incredibly
powerful. It can also uh save this in a
Google Doc or Google Sheet. So, it can
do a lot. Um I just I I do think though
that Open Claws better if you're willing
to get past the technicalities of it
because it it it's unlimited as far as
it's use case it's not limited by
anything. It's not limited by a
particular platform.
Uh, it can use any tool that it wants,
right? So, you can use anything. You
don't just have to use Claude, right?
And so, I think there's advantages
there.
Um, but you know, if you want to have
something a little more secure something
a little bit safer, something a little
more potentially reliable in some cases,
um, this is it. Now, I will tell you
using this browser extension
be careful, okay? Because there's a
couple things that will happen. Number
one is when you get really long jobs, it
can break and it will like it will just
kill the job and then your work can get
erased. Uh, I've also had this uh,
the browser's crashed many times. So,
when the browser crashes, anything that
you have in here that's been collected
gone. It's absolutely gone. Does not
save. Now, this could be user error on
my end, but I have not found a way to
properly save the data when you're using
just the pure browser extension like I'm
doing now. It doesn't like go into
Claude, right? So,
um, as soon as it finishes a job, the
first thing you want to do is copy that
information and go and put it into a
Google Doc just to make sure because if
it crashes, you're going to lose it,
okay?
So, that's what I would be thinking
about on this and this is once again one
simple use case for agents where you
just, you know, use good solid prompts
and let the agent go and do your link
prospecting, do your
uh, one I just did recently was for uh,
finding opportunities inside uh, for
Rankability that we had a bunch of
outdated logos and stuff like that. I
had this go and do that. Another simple
one is I had
uh, Claude go and
um, update our G2 profile, okay? So, I
actually had it I had was logged in in
G2 and I let it change all of the
settings. So, I said, "Hey, good you
know, go to our website and make sure
that um our G2 profile is up to date
with the most current information and
it's 100% accurate." So, then it went
through, literally cleaned up the whole
G2 profile. I didn't even touch it and
it just did it, right? And uh so, small
little things that you can do on that
front are going to be incredibly
valuable uh using agents. Uh there's
obviously small use cases and big use
cases outside the scope of this video,
but um but yeah, agents are the key to
execution. Now,
there's one thing that really, really
matters to all of this, okay? The
technology is no longer a problem. The
knowledge of the AI is no longer a
problem. Um the the uh the capabilities,
honestly, is not really a problem
anymore. The biggest problem I'm seeing
with people trying to use AI or use
agents is you still need to understand
the process, right? Like, you you know,
you give these incredibly high-powered
tools to someone that does not have any
experience doing SEO, doesn't have any
systems, has never driven results, it's
not going to do anything for you, okay?
The key to really getting the best
results with this technology is
understanding the process of SEO, okay?
You have to know how does this all work
from end to end, okay? And so, that's
why in these videos that I'm going to be
doing here on my YouTube channel,
this is the first one, which is, you
know, what is SEO in 2026? Let's let's
get this high-level overview explained.
All of the upcoming videos, I'm going to
be unpacking every little detail of SEO,
okay? We're going to dive into this um
because there's just so much. There's so
much to know, so much to do
um to do this the right way, okay? And
no, Chat GPT is not going to help you.
No, or some random guy on X who's never
done SEO is not going to help you with
this because there's so much nuance and
so much detail that goes into building a
proper SEO system from end to end.
Um and you know, at the end of the day,
Chat GPT on its own has never developed
a strategy, executed a strategy, and
iterated on that strategy in its entire
existence, okay? All it ever does is
just give you information that it's
found, and that's it. But it's never
actually executed that work. Now, at
this point, agents can execute. Uh they
can execute, but they can only execute
within the confines of a proper
strategy, a proper system. And so that's
what I'll be talking about in these, you
know, many videos I'm going to be doing
here. Um and if you want like my most
up-to-date stuff, like if you want to
see like the like the stuff that I'm
constantly updating, my systems,
um everything that I'm doing as far as
AI and SEO specifically, uh Search OS is
probably the best place for that, okay?
So you can see in Search OS.
This is the platform where I manage all
of um all of our work across all of our
campaigns, all of our businesses, not
just SEO, but like literally all of our
work. Like you can see we go into you go
into Rankability, like we have our
engineering in here. Like this is like
engineering for our product. Like
everything is managed in here.
Um and funny enough, uh if you want to
know, this is my OpenClaw
uh bot here. So Serena, okay? So this
is, you know,
she goes and she manages all of the
operations in here. Um but Search OS is
much more than just that. It's
obviously, when you click in here,
you're going to be able to see
um any of these. You'll be able to see
this, you know, we're starting to uh
upload stuff to the academy now, so you
can see this is the local SEO and AI
search playbook is all being built in
here.
But if you also go, this is where the
real magic happens, is every single
thing that we do is systematized, right?
So, hundreds, now hundreds of SOPs in
here specifically for local and now
we're starting to build in some
SaaS-related stuff as well.
Uploading the agent skills, so as we
build skills with our own agents, we
just go ahead and put the the templates
in here so you can copy of them and
start to build your skills with your
agents as well, okay? So, there's a ton
of stuff in here and I've just
putting new things in here. So, if you
want really like
you want to figure out how to really do
this the right way, this is probably
going to be the best place to go. So,
I'll have a link below the video. In the
next video, we'll start digging into
some, you know, really hardcore SEO
stuff, but hopefully this helps you get
a good idea of, you know, ultimately
what SEO is all about right now.
And I'll see you in the next video.
Thanks.